howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to gym
rut show.com
that's Jim ruts show com this is another
in our extra koban 19 episodes they're
shorter the audio quality won't be as
good but the intellectual content will
be every bit as good today's guest is
Robin Hansen a professor of economics at
George Mason University and he has some
very interesting and perhaps to some
people startling ideas about how to
manage the Koba 19 virus and what
lessons we should learn from this to be
ready for next time why don't we start
out Robbin with the idea of dosage
effects something I've seen relatively
little in the media the idea that the
strength of the infection you get and
hence the risk of having the infection
is in some fashion linear or nonlinear I
don't know probably related the amount
of exposure one gets what can you say
about that well I've seen 3d articles
over the last couple weeks one in the
New York Times one of the New Yorker and
one in a British paper so it's not
completely neglected and the usual tone
is well people make the simplifying
assumption that you're either infected
or not but there's actually the subtly
and it's kind of interesting and there's
this literature on it and in fact in the
medical literature there is this huge
literature on what they call viral load
because that's relatively easy to
measure that is they they look in your
bloodstream and see how many viruses
there are and that correlates with a lot
of think people with higher by hour load
typically have more symptoms and die
more and all those sorts of things now
the initial viral load is what we're
talking about as a dose that is the
moment you get infected
how big a chunk do you get now people
believe that that makes a lot of
difference
and that's one of the main rationales
wearing masks because not just to cut
the chance of an infection but to cut
the dose that you get when you get it
but in terms of research it's thin
because it's hard to actually control
and measure the initial dose we don't do
a lot of infecting people on purpose in
order to measure that so but there is a
long history not only do we have like
two studies in the last few decades
where we've seen an effect of dose on
death rates for humans for a virus one
is measles whereas about a factor 14
another is SARS or is about a factor of
three
and these are different variations in
the dose that naturally happened but two
centuries ago over we used to do low
dose infection of smallpox as a
deliberate way to reduce deaths so for
example George Washington at Valley
Forge a big set of US troops in Canada
got wiped out which is why the u.s.
doesn't control Canada at the moment and
then George Washington's troops at
Valley Forge were threatened and so he
adopted variolation which was reduced
the death rate from a typical 20 to 30
percent from smallpox down to one to two
percent and that was the a deliberate
small dose so we know there's this big
effect so some people talk about in the
media but there's two things they
haven't mentioned and I'm not sure
because they don't know about it or kind
of scared to mention one is that it
creates it makes lockdowns more
problematic so two extreme kinds of ways
you get a a dose one is by say kissing a
family member or spending a lot of time
close to a venue member and then you're
likely to get a big dose if they're
infected and you aren't kissing them
first moment they got infected then
you're gonna get a lot another way you
might get infected to say touching a
door handle somewhere out in the world
where somebody else touched it in the
last few hours and in that case you're
likely to get a small dose or say
walking past some of who's breathing in
life and you know those low doses would
have much lower mortality rates in
according to the data we've seen that
say a factor of 3 to 30 and so with lock
downs we are slowing the rate at which
people get infected but unfortunately
raising possibly the death rate when
they do get infected
by a plausibly large margin that's
that's a concern so we need this
lockdown to be worth it on the other
organs to be willing to pay that cost
has anybody looked at simulation
including that effect I don't know that
they have I've heard these I haven't
seen anybody pass that along to some
other you know Santa fans do we have a
number of epidemiology modelers in our
community I will pass that idea along to
them and maybe connect you guys up and
maybe some somebody can run a model and
say alright how good does the social
distancing effect have to be to overcome
the intensification effect so the
trade-off is many people are hoping that
we can just with lockdown shut this
virus down and mean most people never
get so you know if only 5% of people
ever get this virus then you're saving
the third 95% and that's a pretty big
game so you would be willing to pay a
relatively large cost increasing that
you know 5% risk in order to save the
other 95% but if we're just talking
about everybody getting it but you know
spreading that over time that's a harder
trade-off in my mind because first of
all you're suffering that big economic
cost over a much longer time of the big
block town and secondly of course you
know this question is how much better is
it to get sick when you're not near the
peak of the pandemic because you get
more medical resources you know is that
a factor of 15% is that a factor of five
what is that gain immortality of getting
me more the medical treatment away from
the peak so for example people focus on
ventilators and you know making sure
everybody has them but apparently people
on ventilators three-quarters of them
die anyway benefit of a ventilator can't
be much more than a quarter in terms of
mortality rates which is nothing to
sneeze and I mean if you can get that
benefit you want it but again you know
what other what at what cost so as I
said there's two main effects that
people haven't talked about one is this
dose effect increasing death rates in
lockdown and the other is the prospect
of reducing death rates by just
deliberately infecting people and this
is what they used to do with small pox
centuries ago it was called variolation
and again it was considered this great
historical triumph to drastically reduce
deaths rates from smallpox which were
really wiping Europeans out of course
this was something the Chinese and the
Indians and actually a great most a
great many of the Africans who were
brought to the US as slaves they had
undergone this treatment back in Africa
and so you know say the United States
this information was available to them
but they just refused to listen or
believe until prestigious enough people
from that royal society etc talked about
it now you have an advocating straight
up that we consider a program of you
know structured variolation
to attack COBIT 19 could you tell us
about your ideas there so as you know a
lot of people have a lot of ideas and a
lot of ideas should be explored there's
many different vaccines people have to
test them they should be tested as fast
as possible but this variolation concept
that considered is very reliable I mean
the the odds are very high that it works
of course you still test it so I think
we should try with intestine one hundred
or a thousand people where you just try
different ways to dose them in different
ways it gets in the body etc maybe
antivirals as a compliment
well but after that I am really quite
sure at least you know 80 90 percent or
more that you'll get good results and
then you know say a factor of five in
death rates you can then drastically
reduce how many people are fracking now
what you actually want to do is to
attract volunteers for this you don't
necessarily have to force people and
then you'd have a place where they were
go to get infected then stay isolated
until they were covered if you just
infect people but then let them you know
go around then you're just accelerating
the pace of the whole pandemic
whereas if you isolate them as soon as
you infect them you actually can be
slowing down the pace of pandemic that's
spreading out flatten the curve so the
key concept is after an initial trial of
roughly a thousand figure out how to
dose and you know properly in fact
people isolate them in what I call hero
hotels where
you pay to go in and you can't leave it
so you're recovered and then try to get
as many of these things open and as many
as what to come in voluntarily and maybe
even subsidize it get health plans to
properly the costs etc and that's the
key idea certainly for the upfront cost
no reason not to incentive heavily take
ten thousand dollars right you'd get a
shitload of volunteers for ten grand
young and healthy people who it's not
just really I mean you know we're a lot
of people are really hurting because
they can't work and they like to go back
at work any of us they'd like to
socialize and as soon as you are
recovered from this you are verified and
certified to work and socialize yeah
that'd be great get part you know part
of the deal is you maybe get a small
stipend to you know to do it and then
you get a certificate that says you're
immune now of course that's assuming
which seems very very likely from the
history of viral infections that you
will get you know at least a year's
immunity from an exposure I have yet to
see that definitively from anybody
though have you seen any reports on
whether an infection actually does give
immunity so the key concept is that when
you recover that is your immune system
pushing it out so at the moment of
recovery you are mu and that's what it
means your immune system pushed down if
your immune system wasn't involved then
of course not but almost always it's
your immune system forcing it out so the
question isn't are you immune it's how
long were you and that friends on
basically the virus changing over the
coming months and years so there are
some viruses that change really fast
such as HIV in which case immunity
hardly last of all but that's very rare
so we have good reason to expect just on
the usual distribution viruses that this
won't be such thing and we do see the
mutation rate on this one being modest
and typical not enormous like HIV yeah
fact I've read and though this was
before there was millions of hosts that
the mutation rate was quite a bit lower
than influenza which might indicate that
you'd have multi year immunity so of
course the mutation rate is proportional
the number of people have it so you
wouldn't see a very high mutation rate
that's not yes it's that be a very
important number for the CDC to be
tracking and getting out to people who
are thinking about these strategies
communities only three months may not be
worth the hotel right you know we're
facing a really dire prospect here uh
you know the odds are really quite good
that basically over half the world will
be infected in the next year our
attempts to suppress this are not going
bird well they're still hoping we should
try but we need a plan B and a plan B
that can cut death rates by a factor
five should be pretty damn tempting this
should at least inspire initial task not
only if you guys were worse yep
and not just the it's really two parts
that we went from this one is cutting
the death rate but second is managing
the socio-economic implications on the
back side of the curve which is where
our society really needs to start being
focusing its attention because you know
we don't handle this right we could
crash the whole socio-economic system in
a very ugly way and the earlier we get
people back to work in a safe fashion
the better so I think your proposal
actually addresses two important factors
is the prospect of a lockdown for say
five years until a vaccine is finally
delivered is really daunting I mean we
can handle a lockdown for a couple of
weeks but there's not really much
prospect of ending this in a couple of
weeks what many people are hoping is
that they could reduce it within a
couple of weeks enough so that a massive
test and trace would hold it down
but even that is really ambitious it's
far more than we've ever done with
previous pandemics and at the moment
this lockdown isn't actually cutting the
growth rate to a negative Rose rate we
might be slowing into a lot it's lower
positive growth rate but it's still
positive at the moment well sure well
you know H it came late if we look
what's happening in Italy in Spain and
in California and Washington the curves
have been bent there so I believe that
in those places that have put reasonable
lock downs on we will see a bending of
the curve the next two weeks but your
point is still well taken to manage the
backside of the curve is gonna require a
very dynamic dance of really strong sort
valence contact tracing which the United
States has sucked at and then the
reimplementation of pretty draconian
social distancing in in the new hot
spots on the backside there's you know
with a herd with no immunity hot spots
are gonna reoccur and you can let them
spread they're gonna take off again we
do have some hope though from places
like Taiwan and Singapore and Hong Kong
that with enough testing and with enough
tracking and was strong enough
quarantine
maybe we can manage it for the year and
a half until we have the vaccine again
it's a week maybe I mean we should
pursue it but we really need a strong
plan B because I grouse likely we're
gonna need to invoke 10 B so even places
like Singapore and Japan who seem to
have been doing okay as the places
around to get more and more infected
they get more and more a wave of things
coming across the border to handle then
it gets harder and harder and there's a
basic fact about Exponential's
exponential growth is if you have a
bunch of different exponential growth
all added together
it's the highest growth rate that
dominates and so unfortunately you know
if unless they can be completely
isolated from one another whatever
producing the highest rose rate then it
leaks into the rest and then the total
growth rate is dominated by the highest
one so it's not enough to point to the
three best places you have to wonder
about the three worst we don't know
what's going to happen in the third
world whether people whether the warmer
moisture temperatures will cause it not
to go exponential whether there's
built-in immunities for similar things
who knows but that could be they
actually untalked about major reserve if
you know the the global South becomes
utterly overwhelmed by this thing well
even in the United States where we
haven't traditionally had strong borders
between the states it just takes a few
states like New York who don't keep it
under control who for whom a lot of
people leave and go to other places to
overwhelm the good efforts of people in
other places who would otherwise do you
lock down very good well I think this is
a very important idea and I hope that
people think about it I will pass it
along to the modelers that I know at
Texas and Northwest northeastern
and where else few other places the
people in our Santa Fe Institute
community who are doing state of the art
and in fact some of the two of them are
part of the team that Trump and his
people are relying upon okay I will I
will make the offer I did some modeling
myself before I realized that this dose
effect was an important deal just that
the idea of deliberate infection even
without the dose effect and even there I
found gains and I analyzed the
difference between deliberately
infecting the young and healthy versus
the old and sick and who else you might
put quarantines and I found compared to
sort of a baseline model where you
randomly put people in quarantine a
model where you deliberately put the
oldest people in quarantine and you
deliberately infect the youngest people
gives a 40 percent reduction in death
rates so I was pretty excited about that
before I realized there were these
factors of three thirty cool and you
know these are folks who already have
big comprehensive models take the
consideration a whole bunch out so
perhaps you could merge merge how you
very much prefer somebody's professional
experience model to be modified to
include these in facts rather than to
rely on my amateur I will make those
introductions as soon as we're done or
at least by the end of the day on to our
second topic you know you recently
posted that long ago Nations didn't have
standing armies you know basically they
united states didn't have much with
standing army before World War two I
think our army was smaller than
Portugal's but today goddamn huge
amounts are spent on standing armies all
around the world shouldn't we be getting
serious
you know this pandemic is not gonna be
the last one hell we've had four or five
of them in the last twenty years and you
know I've come around to the view people
talk about wisdom topic I've always been
skeptical about sequel whew for my taste
but I've concluded that perhaps
operational wisdom in the modern world
consists of two things one understanding
the concept of fat-tailed distributions
in the second the concept of
Exponential's and pandemics look like
they hit on both so it's a fat-tailed
distribution we're gonna continue to
have pandemics and this is by far not
the worst possible pandemic you know we
could have something that was more
contagious and more lethal so it's
there's a balance there as we know from
epidemiology and so this idea of
you know building much greater standing
capacity seems like a very good one tell
us more about that
well so that was just a tweet I made
that some other people resonated with
and it does make sense but I'd like to
focus less on capacity and more on
flexibility so what I'm struck by is
this very basic phenomena in in the
world of human history where ended of
history of biology where you tend to
have a split between specialized
solutions to two specialized problems
and environments and more general
flexible solutions that are better able
to adapt to changes so for example as
you know humans in particular we're not
the fastest runners were not the
sharpest teeth etc we specialized in
being general and flexible and we found
a niche where in environments that
changed rapidly enough or where we
ranged over wide enough environments we
could win compared to more specialized
predators that we are competing against
and similarly an industry in society you
may have a firm that's in a very stable
industry and then very stable product
and then along comes a new product or a
new variation and they just fall apart
because they haven't acquired
flexibility and generality they've just
been tuned to that very particular
environment whereas say like famously
Intel or companies like that their motto
was everything's going to be changing
all the time don't get stuck with any
one things constantly be ready for
change in flexibility and militaries
similarly as you may know many times in
the past of military has lost war
because they were so ready for the
previous war that they couldn't flexibly
enough change and adapt to the new war
and part of the reason the Allies won in
world war two is that we happen to be
exceptionally flexible compared to
competitors and I'm concerned that you
know not only our militaries over the
last few decades haven't actually been
facing difficult Wars where they needed
flexibility to win but many of our other
social institutions have atrophied even
our legal and regulatory institutions
have assumed an environment it's going
to be pretty stable as they seen it and
then when you get a big disruption like
the one we've just seen they just can't
adapt they're just not ready for it and
see that is some of the biggest problems
we've seen with response to code 18 is
that our regular curry institutions our
medical institutions just couldn't adapt
very fast they weren't ready for that
there was no place so if you want to put
a standing army in response to the two
medical problems I'm happy to devote the
resources but if you just give more
resources to the same organizations
around the same way I fear they will
atrophy in the same way they will get
locked down into rules and regulations
and procedures that work well over
stable decades and then fail terribly
when all the sudden things change fast
and they need to adapt fast and of
course it's not just pandemics that this
is about you know we it's financial
panics its potential cyber attacks on
our key infrastructure it's solar flares
in fact one of things I'm contemplating
is that we really ought to have a
department of wicked risks looking at
complex systems risks that involve
surveillance since making decision
making and then pass off the action
doing to other people because the thing
that shocked me the most about this damn
things a lot of things that shocked me
about it but one of them is how
unbelievably inept the whole West has
been in taking a pretty damn clear
signal by say the 20th of January that
there was a non-trivial risk and some
hedging ought to be done at you know the
hundreds of millions of dollars of love
Louisville and partial mobilization
begun just as an intelligent risk the
same way a trader with a portfolio would
have hedged a risk when they saw a trend
going adversely and yet as far as I
could tell you know the chief executives
of the major countries we're caught
blindsided didn't weren't even aware of
this damn thing until the 1st of March
so there was you know five or six weeks
which is about ten doublings of the damn
thing before the censors who had
detected that there was something going
on that needed to be hedged and action
and mobilization needed to be started
nothing happened or very very little and
so the you know the whole combination of
monitoring and sense making and decision
digestion just
you said it seems to have atrophied and
failed in our society in a way that is
surprising and bad so you know that the
Romans had this policy to always be at
war somewhere so that their military
didn't lose the edge and flexibility and
experience to be able to fight a war the
question now is you can assign a budget
and an agency and tell them to be
flexible but how do you make them
actually be flexible so we might ask how
did these Asian nations succeed and be
more flexible part of it is they are
more autocratic and you're looking at
the high tail of the most functional
autocratic ones and a lot of low tail up
the dysfunctional ones part of is they
faced SARS and a scary epidemic just a
decade ago and so they created
adaptations for that and were more ready
for that so we didn't face that we
weren't scared so we didn't you know set
ourselves up for it I'm not sure what
else to explain other than just sort of
look over the last few decades a lot
more it's been changing in Asia their
governance has had to deal with rapid
rates of change in a lot of aspects of
society whereas ours it's not we our
government in our society has been
pretty stable for 70 years and a lot of
people think no need to change the way
we do things things have been going
pretty well yeah I think that those are
all real issues and of course it also
goes to our governance I mean again look
across the West the leadership that we
have where's the Winston Churchill's
where's the FDR it's worse even the
Joseph Stalin's right
it's basically lightweights and clowns
that are the chief executives across
most of the West right and that can't be
the formal system is still roughly the
same formal system that has to be
culture and you know our informal you
know professions and other habits yeah
well unfortunately made the profession
of politics toxic right you know no FDR
would put himself through the grinding
humiliation of the current political
process to become president United
States when he could sit back fat dumb
and happy and is with his millions of
dollars on his estate very very few
people I posted on this several times
you know I know 20 people personally who
would be better chief executives
the United States than the current one
that's just people I know but not a
single one of them would run for dog
catcher because of the you know the
negative consequences of putting your
name out into the public sphere these
days I'm afraid of the democracy the
voters have to take it out of the blank
okay they do the borders and the
institutions around the voters yes media
indeed one of the video response to the
voters largely it's the voters to drive
the media and the voters right now maybe
you would think of like the institutions
of law or civil service professionals as
also responsible for the resulting
current state of those institutions in
areas we do need institutional cleanup
maybe this will be a call probably not
but at least there'll be some people
with ears to hear that will start the
process going well Robin I want to thank
you for as all he's an incisive
intellectually powerful conversation and
I think our audience will have learned
quite a bit this is a great great
talking to you it's always great and I
will send those connections out to the
epidemiologists later today okay
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]